A Guide to the Library of Virginia, Public Services and Outreach Division, Highway Historical Marker Records, 1928-1975
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia, Public Services and Outreach Division, Highway Historical Marker Records, 1928-1975
The Library of Virginia
27998
19.5 cu. ft. (40 boxes)
Library of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Publications and Educational Services Division, The Library of Virginia, 8 March 1973.
Biographical Information
Virginia's historical marker program is the oldest such program in the nation, beginning in 1927 when a handful of markers were erected along U.S. 1 between Richmond and Mount Vernon. Originally the Conservation and Economic Development Commission was tasked with creating historical markers. In 1949, the Virginia Department of Highways was assigned the responsibility for installing and maintaining new markers, and in 1950 the Library of Virginia took over researching and approving new makers. In 1966, management of the highway markers was transferred to the newly created Virginia Landmarks Commission, the predecessor agency of the Department of Historic Resources. Today VDOT retains primary responsibility for installing new markers and maintaining existing ones. In this capacity, VDOT is a vital partner with DHR in managing the marker program.
More information on the marker program and an online database search is available at: Virginia Department of Historic Resources Historical Highway Markers
Scope and Content
Records, 1928-1975, including charts and keys, clippings, correspondence, inscriptions, invoices, maps, negatives, notes, photographs, and publications of the Highway Historical Markers program in Virginia. The collection is arranged into two series, Series I: Administrative records and Series II: Marker inscriptions and photographs. These records trace the design, construction, wording, and images of the Highway marker program in Virginia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Administrative records, 1928-1975
Series II: Marker inscriptions and photographs, 1928-1975
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative records, 1928-1975., Extent: 5.4 cu. ft. (12 boxes). (Box 1-12)
  Records, 1928-1975, including charts and keys, clippings, correspondence, histories, invoices, lists, orders, price lists, and publications documenting the administration of the Highway Historical Marker program in Virginia. Included is correspondence with members of the Advisory Committee, including Dr. Thomas Abernathy, Dr. Cannaday, and Dr. Swem; correspondence regarding the research involved in locating historical sites, correct spelling of signs, and the placement and ordering of signs; correspondence from other states requesting information on Virginia's highway marker program; requests and suggestions for signs; and correspondence regarding funding issues throughout the years [including wartime restrictions on materials]. Also included is correspondence with the highway Department landscape engineers regarding the erection and replacement of various markers. Of note is the folder containing histories, memorandums, and policies of the highway program, 1930-1964.
  Included is correspondence and price lists from sign making companies, Lake Shore Markers (Erie, Pa.), and Salem Foundry and Machine Works (Salem, Va.); lists of markers erected, markers needing further work, markers broken, requests for markers, and lists of photographs of markers. Also included are folders relating to the marker coding system and index cards of marker inscriptions, arranged alphabetically. The index cards include the name of the marker, letter code, location, and dates ordered, relocated, photographed, and painted. Some of the index cards include small photographs of the markers.
  Of note are the various editions of the State Historical Markers of Virginia publication and the maps of Virginia showing location of markers [oversize bound volume]. While the bulk of the marker inscriptions are in Series II: Marker inscriptions and photographs, researchers should also check this series for information on marker coding, as well as markers erected, as the information is included in both series.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Advisory Committee, Abernathy, Dr. Thomas P., 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Committee, Abernathy, Dr. Thomas P., 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Committee, Cannaday, Dr. D.A., 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Committee, Cannaday, Dr. D.A., 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Committee, Mason, George C., 1936-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Advisory Committee, Miscellaneous, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Advisory Committee, Swem, Dr. Earl Gregg, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Committee, Swem, Dr. Earl Gregg, 1941-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Advisory Committee, Tynes family, 1946-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1932-1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1952 January-May (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1952 June-December (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1955 January-May (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1955 June-December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1956 January-May (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1956 June-December (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1957 January-May (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1957 June-December (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Inquiries about markers program from other states and countries, 1928-1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Inquiries about markers program from other states and countries, 1950-1957 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Dept. of Highways, Landscape engineers Turner and Neale, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Dept. of Highways, Landscape engineers Turner and Neale, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Dept. of Highways, Landscape engineers Turner and Neale, 1951-1958 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Histories, memorandum, and policies, 1930-1964 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lake Shore Markers, Inc., Correspondence, 1946-1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lake Shore Markers, Inc., Price lists, 1953-1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - List of broken and revised markers, 1930-1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - List of graves of distinguished Virginians, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lists of markers, 1929-1948 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lists of markers, 1949-1960 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - List of markers erected, 1946-1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - List of markers requiring further work, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Lists of payments received for broken markers, 1929-1949 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - List of photographs of markers, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Markers code lettering, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Marker inscription index cards, A-V (Box 6)
  - Marker inscription index cards, W-Z, and Discarded markers (Box 7)
  - Large Highway maps of Virginia showing location of markers [bound volume] (Box 39)
  - Marker construction, Specifications, 1932-1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Marker inscriptions, Tentative, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Marker inscriptions, Various, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Marker inscriptions, Private, 1953-1965 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Marker programs, Other states, List, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Marker programs, Other states, Alabama-Maryland, 1941-1959 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Marker programs, Other states, Massachusetts-Nevada, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Marker programs, Other states, New Hampshire-Oklahoma, 1951-1959 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Marker programs, Other states, Pennsylvania-Vermont, 1951-1961 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Marker programs, Other states, Washington-Wyoming, 1951-1965 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Marker requests, Halifax County, 1936-1948 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Marker requests, Lynchburg, 1931-1951 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Marker requests, Various, 1947-1949 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Marker request, Various, 1950-1952 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Marker requests, Various, 1959-1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Marker requests, Not under consideration, 1928-1951 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Permits for placing markers, 1941-1947 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Publications, Key to Inscriptions on Virginia Highway Historical Markers, 1st Edition, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Publications, Key to Inscriptions on Virginia Highway Historical Markers, Col. Bryan Conrad copy, 2nd Edition, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Publications, The Virginia Highway Historical Markers, First issue, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Publications, Key to Inscriptions on Virginia Highway Historical Markers, 3rd Edition, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 4th Edition, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 5th Edition, Rough draft, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 6-8)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 5th Edition, Daniel's marked copy, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 6th Edition, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 6th Edition, For printers, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 6th Edition, Hemphill's desk copy, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 6th Edition, Official work copy, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 6th Edition, Additions and revisions, 1948-1958 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Publications, State Historical Markers of Virginia, 6th Edition, Additions and revisions, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Salem Foundry and Machine Works (Salem, Va.), Correspondence and orders, 1948-1950 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Salem Foundry and Machine Works (Salem, Va.), Correspondence and orders, 1951-1954 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Salem Foundry and Machine Works (Salem, Va.), Correspondence and orders, 1955-1959 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series II: Marker inscriptions and photographs, 1928-1975., Extent: 14.1 cu. ft. (28 boxes). (Box 13-40)
  Records, 1928-1975, including correspondence, inscriptions, invoices, negatives, notes, and photographs documenting the historic marker program in Virginia. Subseries A. Marker inscriptions includes correspondence, draft and final wording of markers, invoices, newspaper clippings, notes, purchase orders, and requisitions. Includes correspondence regarding replacement of broken markers, and changes, placement, and suggestions for markers. Also includes notes on when the marker was erected and if it was replaced or broken. Subseries B. Photographs includes photographs and negatives of the markers arranged by marker number.
  Arranged by marker number in two subseries: Subseries A: Marker inscriptions and Subseries B: Marker photographs.
  - Subseries A. Marker inscriptions
    - A1 - A15 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - A16 - A30 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - A31 - A39 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - A40 - A49 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - A50 - A62 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - A72 - A94, A135 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - AL5, AL10, AS1 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - B2 - B25 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - B26 - BX7 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - C1 - C29 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - C30 - C90 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - CB1 - CL3 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - D6 - D30 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - E1 - E9 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - E10 - E15 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - E16 - E25 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - E26 - E37 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - E38 - E45 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - E46 - E50 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - E51 - E59 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - E60 - E69 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - E70 - E90 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - EH8 - EP20 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - F1 - F12 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - F13 - F24 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - F26 - F65 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - F66 - F98 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - FA1 - FR25 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - G - GA (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - I1 - I10 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - I11 - I17 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - J1 - J9 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - J11 - J17 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - J20 - J42 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - J60 - J69 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - J70 - J78 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - J80 - J89 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - JD1 - JE6 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - JE15 - JJ10 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - JJ12 - JT5 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - JT6 - JX5 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - K1 - K15 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - K16 - K30 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - K31 - K45 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - K47 - K72 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - K73 - K95 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - K116 - K139 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - K140 - K158 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - K170 - K210 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - K211 - K225 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - K226 - K239 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - K240 - K244 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - K245 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - K246 - K255 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - K256 - K261 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - K262 - K307 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - K306 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - KA8 - KC10 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - KD5 - KG20 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - KG21 - KY4 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - KV7 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - L3 - LT1 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - M9 - M25 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - M26 - MJ1 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - N4 - N21 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - N22 - N85 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - ND4 - NW15 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Norfolk [City] (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - O5 - O25 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - O27 - O39 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - O40 - O49 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - OB2 - OC25 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - OC35 - OQ5 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - PA2 - PA25 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - PA60 - PH6 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Q1 - Q5 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Q6 - Q7 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Q8A - Q8Q (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Q9 - Q11B (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - QA1 - QC1 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - R4 - R80 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - RA4 - RG5 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - S1 - S10 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - S11 - S25 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - S26 - S52 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - S53 - S79 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - SA5 - SN60 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - T1 - T45 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - U22 - U60 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - U80 - U130 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - UC5 - UT28 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - V1 - V21 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - X6 - X15 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - X16 - X30 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - XB4 - XP5 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - W1 - W15 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - W16 - W24 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - W25 - W35 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - W36 - W49 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - W50 - W65 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - W66 - W70 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - W79 - W88 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - W89 - W199 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - W200 - W206 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - W207 - W218 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - WO12 - WP10 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - WY5 - WY16 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - WY17 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - WY88 - WY92 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Z5 - Z98 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Z106 - Z185 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Z187 - Z269 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - County line markers (A-Y counties) (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - County line markers, Various (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
    - Frontier forts (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Norfolk (John Hunter Holt) (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Norfolk's Historic Mace (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Orange County (First German Reformed Church, Germanna) (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - State entrance signs (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Oversize (Box 40)
  - Subseries B. Marker photographs
    - Extra copies, 1951 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Sample markers, 1928 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Sample markers, 1928 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - A1 - A10 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - A11 - A20 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - A21 - A30 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - A32 - A45 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - A46 - A92 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - B2 - B33 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - C4 - C22 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - C23 - C34 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - D30 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - E1 - E9 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - E11 - E20 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - E21 - E50 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - E52 - E60 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - E62 - E72 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - F1 - F20 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - F50 - F75; FB2 - FB4 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - G10 - GA34 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - I1 - I9 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - J1 - J15 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - J29 - J65 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - J66 - J75 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - J77 - J87 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - JT4 - JT12 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - K1 - K20 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - K21 - K30 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - K31 - K40 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - K43 - K75 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - K76 - K140 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - K206 - K218 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - K221 - K239 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - K242 - K250 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - K251 - K260 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - K262 - KC4 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - KD5 - KG20 (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - L3 - LB5 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - M10 - M30 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - N4 - N17 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - N20 - NW9 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - O5 - O15 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - O17 - O45 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - OB2 - OB3 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - PA2 - PA20 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - PA23 - PA144 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Q (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - S2 - S10 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - S12 - S20 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - S21 - S40 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - S41 - S52 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - S53 - S70 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - S72 - S79; SA5 - SA30 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - T3 - T8 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - U25, UE5 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - V1 - V7 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - V8 - V12 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - W2 - W10 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - W11 - W20 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - W21 - W30 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - W31 - W39 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - W42 - W50 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - W52 - W50 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - W61 - W90 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - W149 - W205 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - W206 - W214 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - WY7 - WY92 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - X6 - XB23 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Z1 - Z22 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Z31 - Z50 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Z51 - Z70 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Z71 - Z85 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Z86 - Z100 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Z102 - Z119 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Z124 - Z150 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Z151 - Z170 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Z173 - Z190 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Z196 - Z218 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Z221 - Z224 (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Washington-Rochambeau Route (Box 38, Folder 9)